Guide to the Extension Teaching prize speaking contests records, 1908-1971.
Extension Teaching prize speaking contests records
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Extension Teaching prize speaking contests records, 1908-1971.
21-24-3105
Cornell University. Cooperative Extension. Teaching and Information Department
.7 cubic ft.
printed material, photographs
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Material documenting Prize Speaking Contests held under the auspices of the Oral Expression Division of Extension Teaching, including the Eastman Stage in Public Speaking, the Farm Life Challenge Contest; and the Home Economics Stage in Public Speaking.
ORGANIZATIONAL HISTORY
Beginning in 1908, two Agricultural Stages in public speaking were given under the auspices of the Agricultural Association, with small prizes awarded by the college. In 1910, trustee Almon R. Eastman established the Eastman Stage, with a permanent endowment beginning in 1918. The Eastman Stage was held continually except in 1943 and 1944. The Farm Life Challenge Contest began in 1928 and was later renamed the Rice Debate Stage in honor of Professor James E. Rice. The Home Economics Stage in Public Speaking began in 1940. Later known as the Elsie Van Buren Rice Public Speaking Stage, it was sponsored by the Home Economics Club.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Scrapbook of programs and clippings documenting Prize Speaking Contests held under the auspices of the Oral Expression Division of Extension Teaching, including the Eastman Stage in Public Speaking, the Farm Life Challenge Contest; and the Home Economics Stage in Public Speaking. Includes letters to and from Andrew Dickson White. Also newspaper articles and programs pertaining to the Eastman and Rice Speaking competitions, 1908-1970; photographs of contestants in Eastman, Eastman-Rice, Farm Life Challenge Contests; Speeches from the Eastman and Elsie Van Buren Rice Stage competitions; Scrapbook from George Abram Everett containing information about Cornell University theatrical productions and photographs, 1914-1920.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Cornell University.; Everett, George Abram.; White, Andrew Dickson, 1832-1918.; New York State College of Agriculture -- Students.; New York State College of Agriculture and Life Sciences. Dept. of Communication Arts.; New York State College of Home Economics -- Students.
Subjects:
Public speaking.; Debates and debating.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
CONTAINER LIST
- Scrapbook: Oral Expression Division of Extension Teach. Prize Speaking Contests, 1908-1970 (Box 1)
  Contains photographs of speaking contest winners. Includes programs and newspaper clippings about the Eastman Stage, the Farm Life Challenge Contest, and the Elsie Van Buren Rice Stage. Clippings come from publications including the Cornell Daily Sun, The Ithaca Journal, and the New York Times.
  A few letters to and from Andrew D. White pertaining to Public Speaking Contests
- Annual Rice Debate Stage Photographs, 1932-1935, 1938-1940, 1942, 1943, 1947, 1949-1951, 1954, 1958-1962 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Annual Eastman-Rice Stage Photographs, 1967-1972 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Miscellaneous Contest Photographs, 1930, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  Third Annual Farm Life Challenge Contest, February 10, 1930
  Woodford Prize Speaking, January 6, 1971
- Directories (Box 2, Folder 4)
  Silver Anniversary of the Rice Debate Stage
  Golden Anniversary of the Eastman Stage in Public Speaking
- Eastman-Rice Speeches, 1967-1968 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  1967-Donald R Fox, Margaret Foster "Role of the Modern Woman", Ralph J Hemminger "America's Commitment to the Hungry", Richard Hernan
  1968-Percival Prince "Racial Harmony in a Multi-Racial Society of the British Caribbean", Ira Lipsky, Timothy Schiavoni "The Middle Generation", Brooke Breslow
- Annual Eastman Stage Public Speaking Photographs, 1912, 1914, 1916-1919, 1921-1926, 1928,1929, 1933, 1936, 1938-1940 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Annual Eastman Stage Public Speaking Photographs, 1941, 1943, 1946-1955, 1957, 1960-1966 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Elsie Van Buren Rice Speaking Contest Speeches, 1946-1950 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  1946- Doris Dittman "The Psychology of Fashion", Joan Fulton "Atomic Age Alternatives", Barbara Benisch "Friendship, The Foundation of World Order", Vivian Hoffman "Japan Needs Emancipated Women", Martha Murrell "Woman: The Eternal Homemaker"
  1947-Isabel Cascarella "Women Also Paid", Jean Dunlavey "Women are on a Spot", Unknown "Tolerance is what You Make It", Olga Myslichuk "Women's Rights"
  1948- Elodie Mayer "Qualifications for Leadership", Kessel "The Meaning of Success", Carol Lee "Homemaking Comes First"
  1949- Marilyn Gruenberg " Let's Teach Our Children Religion", Agnes Ronaldson "Educating for Peace", Olga Myslichuk "The Need for Religious Education in our High Schools", Julie Rosenkraus "Complacency- the Enemy Within"
  1950- Margaret Bailey "The Value of Community Organizations", Gertrude Strong "Are You Building America?", Elaine Rose "Summer Camping as an Educational Experience", Cort "Your Life Investment---Health"
- Elsie Van Buren Rice Speaking Contest Speeches, 1951-1956 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  1951- Joanne Gully "Education for Marriage", Laurina J Smith "The Responsibility of Education", Betty Dean "Women Can Bring Peace", Elizabeth Lightfoot "Just a Housewife"
  1952- Elizabeth Dean "Trying Not to Keep Up with the Jones", Nancy Paine,
  1953- Doris Smith "Women as Citizens", Elizabeth Rothermal, Jane Ann Hughes "America's Unsung Heroine", Spangenberger
  1954- Irene Adler, Nancy Paine "Education Toward Marriage", Doris Smith "The College and the Homemaker"
  1955- Mary Neill "What Real Security Means", Ruth Amsden "What Can I Do Now, Mother?"
  1956- Phyllis Rettinger "In Defense of Advertising", Alayne Czurles "Scouting for a Better Tomorrow", Rita Rausch "A Girl Finds Her Place"
- Elsie Van Buren Rice Speaking Contest Speeches, Unknown (Box 2, Folder 10)
  Unknown Title And Date- Rothermel, Elaine Rose, Sally Jane Stephens, Betsy Anne Alexander
  Unknown Author and Date- "Education-Preparation for Life", "Let's Call a Halt!"
  Unknown Date Only- Marjorie Relyea "What 4-H Means to Me", Susan F Cohen "A Woman of Worth", Elaine Wagner "Making Marriage Work", Kathleen Kendrick "What Makes a Home", Margery Schmidt "Vocational Guidance in High Schools", Hazel Bowdren "What 4-H Has Meant to Me", Kendrick "Making the Most of What We Have", Hazel Bowdren "It's A Great Life", Felice Bernstein "Sexuality of Women", Elizabeth Delane "The Woman's Place", Anita Ades "What College has Done for Me", Carol Harris "Our Partners in Education", Ruth Clarke "Religion at Cornell University"
- Scrapbook of Professor George Abram Everett, 1914-1920 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  Contains an unlabeled photograph, Newspaper clippings from various publications, including the Post Standard, Watertown Times, and the Cornell Daily Sun. The clippings vary in content, but generally involve either war or the production of Kermis (which includes a program). Also, a few letters to Professor Everett.